<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="page.xsl"?>

<page name="Installation">
  <card>
    <p>
      <h1>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</h1>
    </p>
        
    <p>
      An all-inclusive <b>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</b> (size: <b>2.4G</b>)
      that contains simulation software and material required for the
      <a href="http://indico.ictp.it/event/9616/">QE-2021</a> hands-on
      courses is available for download from these locations:<br/>
      <blockquote>
        <ul>
          <li> <a href="http://qe2021.ijs.si/download/QE2021.ova">http://qe2021.ijs.si/download/QE2021.ova</a></li>
          <li> <a href="https://users.ictp.it/~igirotto/QE2021.ova">https://users.ictp.it/~igirotto/QE2021.ova</a></li>
          <li> <a href="https://sissa-my.sharepoint.com/:u:/g/personal/pdelugas_sissa_it/EU8n4maxoDNKnEDpqqB-EWoBoHNGWNd-IrPYEyq48tpv1Q?e=RgQ3rY">
            https://sissa-my.sharepoint.com/:u:/g/personal/pdelugas_sissa_it/...</a></li>
          <li> <a href="http://51.75.95.253:81/QE2021.ova">http://51.75.95.253:81/QE2021.ova</a> (low bandwidth)</li>
          <li> <a href="http://51.255.174.94:81/QE2021.ova">http://51.255.174.94:81/QE2021.ova</a>
          (low bandwidth) <br/> (make sure that the downloaded file
          has the extension <b><tt>.ova</tt></b> ; there were reports
          that some file-browsers rename the file extension upon
          download)</li>
        </ul>
      </blockquote>
    </p>
    <p>
      The sha256 checksum of the <tt>QE2021.ova</tt> file:<br/>
      <blockquote>
        <tt>013700560aaa820fa9b5d3f760c5634ea29c67e1d4bc0423d2545c1ae550e68a</tt>
      </blockquote>
    </p>

    <p>
      <i>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</i> image is the same irrespective of
      which operating system you use (Linux, Mac OS, or Windows).
      QE-2021 Virtual Machine depends on the <a
      href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> virtualization
      software (version 6.1) and is based on <a
      href="https://www.debian.org/">Debian OS</a>.
    </p>
    
    <h2>Hardware requirements</h2>

    <p>
      Your computer (laptop or desktop) must support <b>virtualization</b> and
      have about <b>10G</b> of free disk space.
    </p>
    
    <h2>Installation instructions</h2>

    <p>
      To install <b>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</b> follow these steps:
      <ol>

        <li>Download and install <b><a
        href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a></b> (click a
        large blue "Download VirtualBox 6.1" button therein).</li>
        
        <li>After <b>VirtualBox</b> is installed and <b>QE-2021
        Virtual Machine</b> downloaded from one of the above provided
        links, import the <i>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</i> by either
        double clicking it or from <b>File->Import Appliance</b> menu
        of the <i>VirtualBox</i> program.</li>
      </ol>
    </p>

    <h2>How to login</h2>

    <p>
      Once <b>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</b> is <i>imported</i> into
      VirtualBox, click the green "Start" arrow on the VirtualBox
      manager window. After <b>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</b> is booted,
      login screen appears. To login use:
      <blockquote>
        username: <b>user</b><br/>
        password: <b>qe2021</b><br/>
      </blockquote>
    </p>

    <h2>Keyboard settings</h2>
    <p>
      By default a system is set to US keyboard. You can change this
      or add new keyboards by going to (upper left corner of the
      Desktop environment):
      <b>System->Preferences->Hardware->Keyboard</b><br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/keyboard1-cr.png" width="602" height="465"/><br/>
      The following window appears (new keyboard layouts can be added by clicking the "+Add" button):<br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/keyboard2.png" width="429" height="432"/><br/>
      The keyboards can then be switched on the right part of the
      top-panel:<br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/keyboard3-cr.png" width="350" height="173"/><br/>
    </p>

    <h2>Changing the number of CPUs</h2>

    <p>
      If your computer has several CPUs then you can increase the
      number of CPUs that <i>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</i> will use as
      to make the calculations run faster. This can be done as
      follows: close the QE2021 virtual-machine and in the
      <i>VirtualBox Manager</i> select the <i>QE2021 Virtual
      Machine</i> but do not start it. Then press the <i>Settings</i>
      button and in the window that appears select <i>System</i> tab
      and increase (or decrease) the number of CPUs accordingly.<br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/cpus-composite.png" width="764" height="421"/>
    </p>
    
    <h2>Troubleshooting</h2>
    
    <p>
      On some laptops <b>virtualization is disabled</b> by default, if
      you encounter any issues, this is the first thing to check.  In
      general you should <b> reboot </b> the system, enter the <b>
      BIOS </b> and search for a <b> virtualization </b> option and
      make sure it is enabled. Some general instruction on how to do
      this are available <b><a
      href="https://helpdeskgeek.com/how-to/enable-virtualization-in-the-bios/">
      here</a></b>.
    </p>

    <h3>Black screen issue</h3>
    <p>
      If you get a black screen, you may need to change the video
      memory in the Settings. Close the <i>QE2021 Virtual Machine</i>
      and then in the <i>VirtualBox Manager</i> select the <i>QE2021
      Virtual Machine</i> but do not start it. Then press the
      <i>Settings</i> button and in the window that appears select
      Display tab and change (increase) the Video Memory.<br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/video-memory-composite.png" width="764" height="421"/>
    </p>

    <h3>Issue with VirtualBox on Windows 10</h3>

    <p>
      It has been reported that sometimes virtual machine does not
      start on Windows 10, despite virtualization being enabled in the
      BIOS. In this case, see
      <a
      href="https://superuser.com/questions/1391838/virtual-box-is-not-working-on-windows-10">Virtual box is not working on windows 10</a>.
    </p>
    
    <h3>Notice to MAC users</h3>

    <p>
      If <i>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</i> opens in a small window, it is
      possible to solve the problem as follows:
      <ol>
        <li>login (see below) without trying to resize the window</li>
        <li>once desktop environment of <i>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</i>
        appears, click on <tt>Cmd+C button</tt></li>
        <li> if <tt>Cmd+C</tt> doesn't solve the problem, use the
        following menu on the "VirtualBox VM": <i>View->Virtual Screen
        1->Scale to ...</i> (you need to select appropriate value of scaling)</li>
      </ol>
    </p>

    <h3>Problem with high DPI screens</h3>

    <p>
      On high DPI screens, text and icons in the VM may appear too
      tiny. This issue can be solved as illustrated by the below
      snapshot via the <i>View</i> menu of the VM main window.<br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/mac-screen-resolution.jpg" width="600" height="522"/>
    </p>
      
    <h3>Ugly layout upon resizing the VM window size</h3>
    <p>
      If you get an ugly layout of VM's desktop upon resizing the VM
      main window, use the <i>View->Adjust Window Size</i> menu on the
      "VirtualBox VM" as shown below:<br/>
      <img class="snapshot" src="images/VM-corrupted-70.png" width="586" height="501"/>
    </p>
      
    <h3>Other issues</h3>
    <p>
      If there are any other issues or if you are unable to load the
      <i>QE-2021 Virtual Machine</i>, try to search for tips on the
      internet. As a last resort, we will try to help you on-line
      at the beginning of the school.
    </p>
</card>
</page>
